## ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

## **SUMMARY**

Program Manager and Data Scientist with ~8 years of proven success delivering on Objectives and Key business Results. Established and scaled enterprise–level Digital Transformation initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Enabled Data Science's 65% overall AI/ML market share across business functions within British Petroleum's US onshore O&G division (BPX) and independently produced \$997MM in value. Delivered \$500M+ in value annually via patent–pending AI–powered computational chemistry solutions for INFICON's Semiconductor business unit.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present Denver. Colorado

- · Acquired 45% of Exploration & Development's AI/ML market and enabled the team's 65% AI/ML market share across the organization directing and executing Data Science & ML Engineering Digital Transformation strategy.
- · Delivered all planned Q2 2024 Agile Features in Data Science and ML Engineering within the project scope.
- · Managed and productionalized the Long-term Production Risk Assessment app via Streamlit for Reservoir Engineering.
- · Oversaw the Azure cloud to AWS cloud Salt Water Disposal and Productivity Index report migration.

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- Generated \$977MM in the Bone Spring formation with a well development plan NPV of \$700MM, Drilling & Completions cost reductions of \$250MM, and core collection avoidance amounting to \$27MM launching AI Lithofacies Prediction in SLB Techlog, enabling regional fluid mobility assessments, and facilitating well development prioritization.
- · Drove \$20MM in annual value for Eagle Ford Reservoir Engineering and a 500% efficiency gain in their well prospecting & assurance workflows productionalizing the ML Refracturing Production Forecasting model via Streamlit.

Data Scientist

INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- · Directed \$500M+ in forecasted annual cost reductions and provisioned Neural Processing Units to support patent—pending Automated Sensor Calibration advances directly on next—generation semiconductor sensor technologies.
- · Led a 21% enhancement in Mass Spec signal fidelity (SciPy.optimize/Statsmodels), designed A/B Quality Control tests (SciPy.stats/Nolds) for all Mass Spec sensors, and documented mathematical foundations for proprietary algorithms.
- · Established 50% coverage across chemical detection and monitoring systems designing KPIs and executing A/B simulation tests via synthetic GC–MS data generated using PySwarms and SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate.
- · Achieved a 95% increase in density estimation accuracy inventing the Bijective Neural Architecture via PyTorch.

Research Assistant

Syracuse University | Data Lab

June 2017 – August 2017 Syracuse, New York

· Modeled social media engagement metrics, formulating repeated measures experiments, utilizing Scikit-learn and NLTK.

Technology Analyst

June 2016 – August 2016

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Jersey City, New Jersey

· Developed project business cases alongside senior team members and deployed code to live internal JPMC applications.

Software Engineer

Self-employed

 $\begin{array}{c} {\rm June~2015-September~2015} \\ {\rm ~Syracuse,~New~York} \end{array}$ 

· Engineered information retrieval systems for **British Petroleum** and local government clients as a subcontractor.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Syracuse University | Hosein Research Group

August 2014 – May 2015 Syracuse, New York

Syrucuse, New 101k

· Awarded the **Dean's Leadership Grant** supporting simulation studies quantifying energy loss across solar cell surfaces.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors August 2023 USPTO Application 18/686,753 Patent Pending INVITED PRESENTATIONS Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing July 2024 BP Geophysics R&D Seminar Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity November 2020 INFICON Data Analytics Summit Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches April 2018 Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT April 2024/December 2023 Core Analysis Workshop UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX April 2023 Havens Consulting Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics June 2019 Dr. S. Joe Qin, President of Lingnan University **HONORS & AWARDS** Graduate Merit Scholarship August 2017 - May 2018 Syracuse University Summa Cum Laude May 2017 Syracuse University The Warren Semon Prize May 2017 Syracuse University Dean's Leadership Grant September 2014 Syracuse University Dean's List August 2014 - May 2017 Syracuse University

The Founders' Scholarship August 2014 - May 2017

Syracuse University

**EDUCATION** 

Syracuse University May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University May 2017 Summa Cum Laude

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Business Strategy, Business Development, Stakeholder Management, Agile Project Management, OKRs, CRISP-DM Technical Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Transfer Learning, Machine Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling, Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Monte Carlo, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Collection, Data Preprocessing, Data Analysis, Data Wrangling, Data Mining Tools AWS SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, SciPy, Statsmodels, NumPy, NLTK,

Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog, Atlassian Jira, Azure DevOps